Review for today's דף daf is ע"ט Ayin Tes 79. We're going
to pick up at the bottom of ע"ט Ayin Tes עמוד ב'
Amud Beis because things got a little confused at the end of
yesterday.
So we're now discussing what type of שיעור shiur is required for
various objects and when various objects can be considered significant in carrying
on שבת Shabbos and when various objects are considered to sort of
have become you know used their purpose and therefore really serve no
purpose. So we discussed it the other day about like a receipt
for having paid the taxes and now we're talking about a שטר,
shtar, a writ of debt that has already been paid up so
it can't be used to collect anymore. So what is the what
is the שיעור? shiur? You know what? Let's start from the two
dots, we'll do it all from the beginning I mean whatever from
the beginning of this discussion about eight lines before the lines get
wide on ע"ט Ayin Tes עמוד ב'. Amud Beis. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught. המוציא
שטר חוב עד
שלא פרעו, Hamotzi shtar chov ad shelo pira'o, you took out a
writ of debt if the debt has not yet been paid חייב,
chayav, then you're obligated because then obviously it's an object of significance
you can use it to collect your debt. משפרעו, Mishe-pira'o, after it's
been paid פטור, patur, you're exempt. רבי יהודה אומר אף משפרעו חייב
מפני שצריך לו Rabbi Yehuda omer af mishe-pira'o chayav mipnei she-tzarich lo
because it has no use. Now there's a question why doesn't it
have use to use as a bottle stopper but okay we won't
worry about that right now. רבי יהודה אומר אף משפרעו חייב מפני
שצריך לו. Rabbi Yehuda omer af mishe-pira'o chayav mipnei she-tzarich lo. Even
after it's been paid you are חייב, chayav, it's an object of
significance because you'll still use the object. Okay. How do you need
the object? So the גמרא Gemara has a couple of possibilities about
what this debate is about.
מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What are they debating? אמר רב יוסף, Amar
Rav Yosef, אסור לשהות שטר פרוע איתא בינייהו. assur lish-ho'os shtar parua
ita beinaihu. The question is is there a prohibition to hold on
to a writ of debt once it's been paid? And that prohibition
obviously would be on the מלוה malveh because you'd be afraid that
after it was paid he would take it out again and collect
again with it. But it would even be on the לוה, loveh,
you know, it's just too dangerous to have around. He would drop
it and the מלוה malveh would find it or somebody would return
it to the מלוה. malveh. So there's a general prohibition to hold
on to a writ of debt once it's been paid or that's
the question. Let's take a look. רבנן סברי, Rabbanan savri, אסור לשהות
שטר פרוע, assur lish-ho'os shtar parua, it's forbidden to have around. If
it's forbidden to have around it has no use, not even as
a use of a bottle stopper. You're supposed to destroy it. Anybody
who's supposed to destroy it no use. רבי יהודה סבר מותר לשהות
שטר פרוע, Rabbi Yehuda savar mutar lish-ho'os shtar parua, you're allowed to
leave it around and since you can leave it around even though
you don't need it and can't use it to collect the debt
but like at least you could use it as a bottle stopper
as a handkerchief something. So therefore that's the debate. So when רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says צריך לו tzarich lo you need it he
doesn't mean you need it to use in its שטר shtar function
but he means who knows you could use it as a piece
of paper and therefore and you're allowed to have it around. That's
one way of saying the debate. Yes.
So when we say a שטר פרוע shtar parua does the שטר
shtar actually on it when it's been paid does it say like
פרוע parua or finished is over it?
No that's why it's a problem. There's no indication on the שטר
shtar that it's been paid and that's why there's this איסור. issur.
So they got a separate receipt?
Yes we'll be discussing that in a minute but yes. Okay. Or
they hand the שטר shtar over to the לוה loveh but maybe
they still said that the even the debtor should not be holding
on to it he should tear it up and destroy it exactly.
So that's the issue. And if you can't hold on to it
it has no purpose you have to destroy it. But otherwise at
least you can use it as a bottle stopper. Okay that's one
answer. אביי אמר, Abaye amar, אביי Abaye says: דכולי עלמא אסור לשהות
שטר פרוע. Dekulei alma assur lish-ho'os shtar parua. Everybody says you're not
allowed to hold on to it if it's been paid and you
can't use it as a bottle stopper. So what possible use could
you have? והכא במודה בשטר שכתבו צריך לקיימו קמיפלגי. V'hacha be-modeh bi-shtar
she-k'tavo tzarich l'kaymo kamipalgi.
The question is if you admit that something has been written does
the
does the creditor still need to authenticate the signatures? So the issue
is again I take out my writ of debt against Charlie here
and it says that Charlie borrowed a million dollars from me and
I got two signatures on it. So obviously I can't get away
with it in בית דין beis din just like that. You have
to know that those are legitimate signatures. Maybe I forged it. So
I have to go and I get them authenticated. I either get
the people actually whose names they are to testify that they're their
names or other people who recognize the signatures and we authenticate the
signatures. That's called קיום שטר, kiyum shtar, authenticating of the signatures. So
I bring the שטר shtar to Charlie he owes me okay we'll
make it a little more reasonable $100,000 okay and I got two
signatures on it ראובן ושמעון. Reuven and Shimon. And Charlie says could
say it's forged you're lying and then I have to authenticate it.
But what he actually says is you know what you're right I
borrowed the money but I paid you up. I just didn't get
back the שטר shtar but I've already paid up that debt. I
forgot to collect the שטר. shtar. So do I have to authenticate
the signatures?
So logically you would say like yeah since he could anyway have
denied it you know and to make it a valid I would
have to authenticate the signatures. But the other argument is no he's
admitted he borrowed the money. So he's admitted this is a legitimate
שטר. shtar. So as soon as he admits he borrowed the money
I don't have to authenticate the signatures. Now I don't have to
authenticate the signatures I've got a שטר shtar he's not believed to
say he paid up if I have a שטר shtar against him
he has to bring proof that he paid up. Totally got himself,
he dug a hole for himself. He admitted it was a good
שטר, Shtar, and now, once it's a good שטר, Shtar, his word
isn't good. Now the obvious response is by the same token, right.
The same token that you believed him that it was a good
שטר, Shtar, believe him that he has paid it up. But that
is the debate. מודה בשטר שכתבו, Modeh b'Shtar shektavo, as soon as
he admits that he wrote it, does he, do I צריך לקימו,
Tzarich l'kaymo, do I still have a need to authenticate it if
I want to collect it against him. Yes.
Would that be a form of מיגו Migo where he says I
paid it but...
Yes, that'd be a form of מיגו, Migo, if you believe me
there, as believe me there. Or another way of saying it is
הפה שאסר הוא הפה שהתיר, Ha'peh she'asar hu ha'peh she'hitir, by the
same virtue, the same mouth that said that I created a problem,
you should believe me that it's not a problem. Okay, so that's
the issue. So how does that play out here? So let's take
a look. תנא קמא... Tanna Kamma... okay, so תנא קמא סבר, Tanna
Kamma savar, the first תנא Tanna that says that it's worthless holds
מודה בשטר שכתבו צריך לקימו. Modeh b'Shtar shektavo tzarich l'kaymo. רבי יהודה
סבר, Rabbi Yehuda savar, מודה בשטר שכתבו אינו צריך לקימו. Modeh b'Shtar
shektavo eino tzarich l'kaymo. So the first one says you have to
be authenticated and the other says that it does not. So still,
how does it play out? ומאי עד שלא פרעו משפרעו, U'mai ad
shelo pra'o mishepra'o, what does it mean when it says once it's
been paid and before it's been paid? Right, we thought it literally
meant before it's been paid and after it's been paid, after it's
been paid does it still have value? So now continuing the דף
ט עמוד א, Daf Tet Amud Aleph, it doesn't mean it's been
paid. It means עד שיאמר לוה פרעתי ולא פרעתי. Ad sheyomar loveh
parati v'lo parati. It means has the creditor, has the debtor said
he paid. Not has it been paid, but has he claimed it's
paid. So now let me just clarify
an assumption that has to be made here that תוספות Tosafot spells
out explicitly, which is he says that it has to be a
scenario, it has to be a scenario where it's understood that I
can't authenticate it. That it's from ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon who
live in מדינת הים, Medinat HaYam, there's no hope that anybody is
ever going to visit us again from Australia
and that's it, there's no hope. Nobody knew them, that's, nobody, so
there's no hope to authenticate. That's the case. Now if Charlie has
not said, has yet to say he paid it, so it has
value, I can use it against him. But if he said he
paid it, so does it have value? Well, if you think that
I still have to authenticate it, it doesn't have value. I can't
authenticate it, that's the scenario, and he said he paid it, so
no value, throw it out, worthless, I'm not חייב. Chayav. If however,
I don't have to authenticate it because he said he paid it,
then it still has value, I can still use it to collect
against him. So that's the scenario: it can't be authenticated, does it
have value? If he hasn't said he paid, then it does have
value, I can use it. But if he said he paid, that's
the debate of whether it still, thank you, retains some value. Now
תוספות Tosafot asks an obvious question. תוספות Tosafot says, I don't get
it. If he hasn't said he's paid, why does it have value?
Right, that's my... Since, since in the end it's all Charlie's decision,
is he going to admit to it or not, my שטר Shtar
is not going to be used to collect the debt. What's really
going to determine whether I collect it or not is whether he's
going to admit to it. But what if Charlie's unsure?
Well, ah, excellent! So that's what תוספות Tosafot says. He says it
still has value, it could remind Charlie, oh yeah, oh, now I
remember that, oh, that then, okay, fine. So it still has that
value. A, so that's does it that, so as a reminder. You
could also say, and it's interesting תוספות Tosafot didn't say this because
the גמרא Gemara says this in other cases, that under certain circumstances
Charlie might be embarrassed to lie. So if I come with no
שטר Shtar and I say you owed me the money, he says,
yala, what are you doing? You're making it up, you're lying, I
never borrowed the money. If I have a שטר, Shtar, even though
technically he believes to say he paid me, it might be more
awkward for him once there's actually this evidence, and that might so
that also could constrain him somewhat. So the שטר Shtar could still
serve a function to get Charlie to admit. Another function תוספות Tosafot
says it could serve is that when, that
if and when Charlie admits, because I have a שטר, Shtar, I'm
able to, I have liens on his on his property, and I
can collect from people he sold the property to. But if there
was no שטר, Shtar, even though he would admit, I could only
collect from like, from his stuff under his control. I could not
collect from people he had sold his property to, there would be
no liens, no שעבודים. Shibudim. So there's a function to this שטר.
Shtar. Okay, so that's the way we've explained this position now. It's
not whether it's been paid or not been paid, but it's a
שטר Shtar that cannot be authenticated and it's whether if it's hasn't
been if there's no claim it's been paid, it's still usable. If
it's been claimed to have been paid, that's the debate of whether
it still serves some function. Now the גמרא Gemara has another possibility.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, again, first wide line of דף ט עמוד
א, Daf Tet Amud Aleph, רבא Rava says דכולי עלמא מודה בשטר
שכתבו שצריך לקימו. D'chulei alma modeh b'Shtar shektavo she'tzarich l'kaymo. Everybody would
agree that even after Charlie says he's paid it, I would still
have to authenticate. Okay, parentheses though, here we are talking about that
I can authenticate it or I did authenticate it.
So forget the debate of whether it needs to be authenticated or
not be authenticated, it's a שטר Shtar that has been authenticated. Okay.
And it's been paid. So what's the issue then about?
והכא בכותבין שובר. V'hacha b'kotvin shovar. Do you write a receipt for
a שטר shtar or not? Okay, so now what's the issue? Because
I take out the שטר shtar against Charlie, he says I paid
it, I says fine, let me write you a receipt. Not when
he originally paid it, a month ago he paid it. I said,
let me write you a receipt. Charlie says, I don't want the
receipt, I want the שטר. shtar. You write me a receipt, I
might lose the receipt. So I'd much, you know, I don't want
you to have a שטר shtar against me and me be responsible
to hold on to a receipt. Give me back the שטר shtar
and I'll cut it up. So the question is, am I entitled
to write him a receipt so that I can maintain the שטר
shtar for my documentation, or is he entitled to demand that I
return the שטר? shtar? And that's the debate. It's an authenticated שטר,
shtar, he paid it up a month ago, but what, am I
entitled to write him a receipt? So let's, well, that's the question.
If I'm entitled to write him a receipt, then there's no default,
that's what he asks for, but if I'm not entitled, I have
to give him back the שטר. shtar. So let's take a look.
So רבי יהודה סבר, Rabbi Yehuda savar, תנא קמא סבר כותבין שובר,
Tanna Kamma savar kosvin shovar, you write a receipt. רבי יהודה סבר
אין כותבין שובר, Rabbi Yehuda savar ein kosvin shovar, you don't write
a receipt. How does that play out? So רש״י Rashi says it's
like this. If basically I write a receipt, okay, so when Charlie
paid up a month ago, I wrote him a receipt. Does this
שטר shtar have any value left? Well, let's see. Okay, what? If
he loses the
receipt? Well, right, right.
Well, value of misuse, right, so a, Charlie doesn't need it, he's
got his receipt. b, I don't have a legitimate use for it
to misuse it. Maybe do I have a use for it to
be like לצר על פי צלוחתא, letzor al pi tzluchasa, to use
it as a bottle stop? So no, I shouldn't be using it
as that either because Charlie might lose his receipt. So basically it
gets back to this issue that I shouldn't be holding on to
the שטר. shtar. Okay? So once he's got his receipt, I have
no real good use for it, no real reason to be holding
on to it, too dangerous, I should be getting rid of it.
If however I didn't write a receipt to Charlie and I'm holding
on to the שטר, shtar, then the שטר shtar has value. What
value does it have? I need to return it to Charlie. I
need to get it to Charlie. So certainly if Charlie has it
has value, so he can, you know, prevent me from having it.
And if I have it, it has value, I have a responsibility
with it towards him. And therefore I would be חייב chayav because
I have to deliver it to Charlie.
It has value to you though, it has value to him.
Yes, but if I have a responsibility with it towards him, then
that's considered to
have value. That's at least the way רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
read it. There's some question of the גרסא, girsa, but we'll leave
it with that. So now רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב
אשי Rav Ashi says, משום דצריך להראותו לבעל חוב שני דאמר ליה
חזי דגברא דפרע אנא. mishum detzarich leharoto lebaal chov sheini de'amar lei
chazi degavra depara ana. He says similar to the idea of why
I want to hold on to my tax collector receipts, right? Charlie
wants to hold on to his,
to the שטרות shtaros that he's paid up because he basically wants
to be able to prove, look everybody, you have any problems? Look,
I've borrowed all this money over the last 10 years, every single
debt I've always paid up. Right? That's actually really important to have
that. Better credit. Exactly, exactly. So therefore it has value and the
other one it's not clear what he would say. Maybe what they've,
again, the concerns that it would be lost and misused and so
on would outweigh those values. Okay, so that's the issue about what
is the minimum שיעור shiur of that object, or to what should
that object have any value. It's definitely not קשי דפז keshi depaz
if you remember, the משנה Mishnah when it started, the כלל גדול
Klal Gadol in the last פרק perek said, first it has to
be דבר שמתצניעין, davar shematznien, it has to be something that has
value to begin with. And number one, it's a minimum size of
value. So here the issue really wasn't of size, it was like
does this thing at all have any value? And that was the
issue about a paid שטר. shtar. Now back to other objects. Or
כדי לעשות. kedei la'asos. So how about if it's leather? So leather
is the amount of leather that you use, this is the minimum
size, to make a קמיע, kamia, to make an amulet, presumably to
wrap around an amulet of either that has some type of a
script in it or some type of herbs or spices or whatever.
So if the leather to make an amulet pouch.
בעי מיניה
רבא מרב נחמן. Ba'ei minei Rava meRav Nachman. So רבא Rava asked
רב נחמן: Rav Nachman: המוציא עור בכמה? hamotzi or bekama? If you
take out leather, how much? This was a lead-up question, right? It's
like you wonder like, okay, why are you asking? What's going to
be the follow-up? That was a, that was a softball. אמר ליה
כדתנן, Amar lei kedetnan, we have our משנה Mishnah says: עור כדי
לעשות קמיע. or kedei la'asos kamia. The amount of leather in order
to make a pouch for an amulet. Okay, העבדו בכמה? hane'avdo bekama?
Some have this גרסא, girsa, some don't, we might as well have
it. So if you actually tan leather, right? To be מעבד עור
me'abed or is a חיוב chiyav on שבת. Shabbos. So how much
is the minimum amount? אמר ליה לא שנא, Amar lei lo shna,
same amount, in order to make, that's the minimum amount of significance.
לעבדו בכמה? le'avdo bekama? How about if the leather is not yet
worked, but your intention is to tan it, is to work it,
but right now it has not been tanned and therefore is not
usable, at least not to make pouches for קמיעות, kamios, maybe you'll
find some other use, but if it's not usable for that purpose
in this form, so what is the minimum size? אמר ליה לא
שנא, Amar lei lo shna, it doesn't matter. Since in the end,
once it is tanned, it'll be usable for this קמיע kamia pouch.
so even untanned that is an amount that has significance cause in
the future this will be an amount that you can use and
therefore this is a minimum amount that has significance even though it
cannot be put to immediate use. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
ומנא תימא, u'mina teiman, where do you know this
from, רבא Rava asked רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, or maybe רב נחמן
Rav Nachman said what do I know it from, where does one
say it from, כדתנן k'ditnan like we turned in the
משנה. Mishna. המלבן והמנפץ והצובע והטווה, hamalben ve'hamanapetz ve'hatzoveia ve'hatoveh, if you
whiten a wool or you comb it or you dye it or
you spin it, שיעורו כמלא רוחב הסיט כפול. shiyuro k'malo rochav hasit
kaful. The amount is double the width of a סיט. sit. What's
the width of a סיט? sit? So the width of a סיט
sit is the distance between if you spread out your thumb and
your forefinger the distance between those two fingers. The distance between your
middle finger and your forefinger is a סיט, sit, the difference between
the two of them is double between the thumb and the forefinger,
double of them it's called רוחב סיט, rochav sit, and it's double
that. So spread twice that length, that is the amount you need
to do the processing of thread to be חייב chayav for any
of those מלאכות. melachos. והאורג ב' חוטין ve'ha'oreg basei chutin and also
you're חייב chayav for weaving two threads, so that is שיעורו כמלא
רוחב הסיט, shiyuro k'malo rochav hasit, if you weave the length of
a סיט. sit. Why do you think the כפול kaful is not
correct? Why is כפול kaful not correct? Why here is it only
one סיט sit and before it was a double a double סיט?
sit?
Because it's thank you, it's two threads, right? So two threads is
basically a double סיט, sit, that amount of thread. Okay, so the
amount of processing the thread, the length, is equal to the length
you're חייב chayav for that amount of thread to weave it. So
he says look what's going on here. You have thread that is
not yet usable for weaving, but the חיוב chiyuv you have in
doing the early stages of preparations is based on the minimum amount
that will be usable once it is done, right? So since the
minimum amount of usable once it is done is this double סיט,
sit, that's the amount that is meaningful even at an early stage.
So there you see you judge the meaningfulness of the early stage
based on the usability once it is done being processed. Let's just
read that, so he says אלמא, alma, you see כיון דלטווייה קאי,
keivan d'litviya kaei, since eventually you're going to spin it and thus
eventually you're going to weave it, שיעוריה כטווייה, shiyurei k'tviya, it's the
same size as when it is spun when it is spun and
how much significance of weaving it's a double סיט, sit, so even
before it's spun that is the amount that is going to be
of significance. Here too, the leather cannot be used right now, but
since it will have this significance once it is tanned, that is
the significance right even right now. Yes Charlie?
Back in the משנה Mishna the measure for leather or animal hide
was for writing, was for writing and now they're comparing it to
something that's going to be used in clothing.
The משנה, Mishna, the leather of an animal hide,
yeah, קלף. klaf. No, but we're talking about עור. or. עור Or
is different than קלף. klaf. קלף Klaf is it's been made into
parchment, okay, that and that we said, that was you know, this
קלף klaf is its parchment. עור Or is still like leather, not
parchment. Okay, if you have a leather pouch, right, you know little
leather pouch, it's not parchment, so it's a different שיעור. shiyur. Okay.
So alright. What's your question? Your question is that why don't you
consider it to be pre-קלף klaf and measure it by the usability
of קלף? klaf? Right. An animal skin can become קלף. klaf. Yes,
so we'll see that in a minute, but the question also is
like here we're talking about that your plan is to tan it
and to use it as leather, it's just early in the process.
What you're saying is let's say it has a couple of possible
paths. Okay, but we're not talking about that yet. We're talking about
you're going to tan it, you're going to make it leather, not
קלף, klaf, and the amount of significance is the amount of significance
it will have once it becomes tanned leather. Okay, so that's his
proof. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with this. הכי
נמי hachi nami here too, כיון דלעבדו קאי, keivan d'le'avdo kaei, your
plan is to tan it, שיעורא כמעובד, shiyura k'me'ubad, the amount is
as if it was already tanned which is the amount to make
a a pouch for for a קמיע kameia for an amulet. So
the גמרא Gemara continued, רבא Rava continued to ask רב נחמן, Rav
Nachman, ושלא לעבדו בכמה, v'shelo le'avdo bekama, let's say you've got untanned
leather that you don't plan on tanning. Now it's not pre-קלף, klaf,
if you right if it if you were planning on turning into
קלף klaf that would be a different discussion, then it would probably
be the size of two letters. But this is not pre-anything,
okay, it's just untanned leather that you have no plans of tanning.
What is the what is the minimum size? Right. So אמר ליה
לא שנא, amar lei lo shna, same point, same difference, no difference.
Okay, so that would be surprising because you're not even planning on
tanning it. Why does it defined by that? Okay, but it presumably
says you know if you don't have any particular plan
so you don't have plans, we have to put it into some
category, presumably it has no use the way it is right now,
we'll put it in the category of stuff that might be tanned
and might be made into it. Okay, but it doesn't really so
much explain his last position, maybe it's somewhat of a default. Okay,
so now איתיביה, eitivei, I'll ask you on this. Is it really
true that things I'm sorry, thank you, ושלא לעבדו בכמה אמר ליה
לא שנא. v'shelo le'avdo bekama amar lei lo shna. Then ולא שני
בין מעובד לשאינו מעובד, v'lo shani bein me'ubad l'she'eino me'ubad, you don't
make a difference between whether it's already Tanned and not tanned, meaning
presumably even if that's your intent, that it doesn't that you really
say that earlier in the process has the same שיעור shiur as
when the process is completed? I'll show you a couple of examples
where things earlier in the process have are different than once it's
completed. Let's take a look. איתיבי, Eitvei, I'll ask you on this.
המוציא סמנים, Hamotzi samanim, if you take out, take out
spices, not spices, you know, things that are going to be used
to actually to make, you know, to make dyes. So whatever they
are, various plants used for dye extraction. So if you take it
out, they already are like some dyes שרויין, shruyin, so it's already,
they've already been sort of steeped in water and the dyes and
have been made. So in, you know, the dye has been
made, then כדי לצבוע בהן דוגמא לאימרא. k'dei litzboa bahen dugma l'imra.
It's enough dye that you would use to dye to color a
sample used for
a loom shuttle. So Rashi says it means a sample the size
of a loom shuttle, or maybe you know, you would take your
sample over to your loom shuttle and compare it with the strands
that you have. But whatever it is, it would be the amount
of dye used to make a certain small sample of cloth. That
is if it's already turned into a dye.
ובסמנים שאינם שרויין, Uv'samanim she'einam shruyin, before they've been steeped in water
and they haven't been turned into a dye, they're just stuff that
you're going to use in that process, תנן, tnan, we taught in
the Mishnah, קליפי אגוזים וקליפי רימונים, klipei egozim v'klipei rimonim, shells of
nuts and shells of pomegranates, סטיס ופואה, istis u'puah, which are different
types of plants used as dyes, כדי לצבוע בהן בגד קטן לפי
שבכה, k'dei litzboa bahen beged katan l'fi shvacha, is the amount that
you would use to turn into amount of dye that could be
used to color to dye a small cloth for the opening of
a hairnet. So whatever that is, that's bigger than a sample. Okay.
So basically the point is if you take out something that's already
dye, it's the amount to color a small piece, a sample. If
you take out the stuff that has yet to be transformed into
dye, it's enough to it's more, it's enough to extract from it
enough dye for a larger garment. So it's more. So the Gemara
says, so you see it's not the same. So איתמר עלה, itmar
alah, no, there's an explanation there why it's different. It was said
about it,
אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah
bar Avuha, לפי שאין אדם טורח לשרות סמנים לצבוע בהן דוגמא לאימרא,
l'fi she'ein adam tore'ach lishros samanim litzboa bahen dugma l'imra, because nobody
goes to the effort to actually, you know, make the dye and
put these things, steep them, for just a tiny little use. So
here's the point of the Gemara.
There's two questions here and the Gemara actually is making, you know,
an important sort of conceptual distinction. Right? One is, I have this
little piece of leather. It is true that I am going to
tan it. I will tan even a little piece of leather and
turn it into a pouch. But maybe the fact that it's not
immediately usable in its current state should mean that it doesn't have
significance even though in the future I have this use for it.
Maybe the fact that it can't be put to that use now
means it doesn't have significance. That's the question of early in the
process and Rav Nachman is saying that doesn't matter. Since that will
be used later, that doesn't undermine its significance now. But the Gemara
says there's another thing, which is not that it should lose its
significance because it's not yet at that stage. It should lose its
significance because I'm never going to turn it into that stage. Okay.
So if I've got a tiny amount of these things that I
can extract dye from, if I'm never going to bother with them
because they're too small to be bothered with, right, then it wouldn't
have significance even though when I had that dye, that dye would
have significance. So if that little piece of leather was not worth
the effort to tan because it was so small, then everybody would
agree it's not a problem. So he says I'm talking about it's
worth the effort to process, you are going to process, it doesn't
lose significance because it has yet to be done. But if you're
not going to bother with it, then I agree with you, it's
not a problem. Okay. And that's going to be the standard answer
to a couple of similar questions.
Let's take a look. And bothering is a function of
size, I suppose more than intention? That is true. Okay. But it's
not because, right, that is true. So אהיי זרעוני גינה, Ahahei zironi
gina, how about seeds for a garden, like for a vegetable garden,
זרעוני גינה דמיקמי דזרעינהו תנן, zironi gina d'mikamei d'zar'inhu tnan,
before they've been planted, we taught in a Mishnah,
זרעוני גינה פחות מכגרוגרת, zironi gina pachos mik'grogueres,
you're taking out seeds like vegetable seeds less than the size of
a pressed fig. How much less? Not clear. רבי יהודה בן בתירה
אומר חמישה, Rebbi Yehuda ben Beseira omer chamisha,
five. Five seeds of cucumber seeds let's say, that's enough to be
חייב. chayav.
That's much less than a כגרוגרת. kgrogueres. Yeah, I know.
ואילו בתר דזרעינהו תנן, v'ilu basar d'zar'inhu tnan, after you've been planted
them, we taught, זבל וכל הדק, zevel v'chol hadak, if you take
out manure or thin sand, somehow a fine sand which was somehow
used in some type of a manure purpose, כדי לזבל בו קלח
של כרוב דברי רבי עקיבא, k'dei l'zavel bo kelach shel kruv divrei
Rebbi Akiva, enough that you need for one head of cabbage, words
of Rabbi Akiva.
No, to fertilize. the chachamim say
the seed is already in the ground okay כדי לזבל
כרשי kdei lezavel kereshi in order to fertilize a leek. So you
see, before it's been put in the ground, it's five- minimum of
five seeds. After the seed has been put in the ground, then
even one seed has significance, right? Then it's even the amount of
manure to for one plant means even it maybe at an early
stage, even when it's just at the seed stage. So you see
it has more significance when it's put in the ground. Why not
even one seed even before it's been put in the ground?
You may say you need to have five in order to get
one of them.
So the גמרא Gemara says well, the גמרא Gemara says essentially the
same. The גמרא Gemara says הא איתמר לה, ha-itmar la, same type
of an answer like we said about the dyes. אמר רב פפא,
Amar Rav Papa, האי דזריע האי דלא זריע, hai de-zria hai de-lo
zria, there's
a difference because one is planted, one is not planted, that we
understood. But לפי שאין אדם טורח להוציא נימא אחת לזריעה, lefi she-ein
adam tore-ach le-hotzi nima achat li-zria,
nobody bothers taking out one seed to plant one seed. You don't
plant one seed. You presumably you might fertilize one plant, but you
don't plant one seed. At least that's the assumption the גמרא Gemara
says. So same idea. It's not- it hasn't lost its significance because
it's not planted. It's lost its significance because nobody's going to bother
to plant it. All right. אמר רב פפא- Amar Rav Papa oh,
we did that. והרי טיט? ve-harei tit? How about plaster? עד דמכמי
דליגבליה, ad de-mikmi de-ligbeleh,
before it's been sort of kneaded, before it's been mixed into plaster,
תניא, tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, מודים חכמים לרבי שמעון
במוציא שופכין לרשות הרבים ששיעורן ברביעית, modim chachamim le-Rabbi Shimon be-motzi shofchin
li-reshut ha-rabim she-shi'uran bi-revi'it, that they agree to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that when you take out dirty water into the רשות הרבים, reshut
ha-rabim,
that it goes by a רביעית revi'it of water. ואוינן בהו, ve-avinan
banu, we say, שופכין למאי חזו? shofchin le-mai chazu? What do you
use dirty water for? ואמרי ירמי להו אגב דנטיתא, ve-amri ye-armeh leh
gabeh de-na de-tita, in order to make plaster. Okay. So it's the
amount of plaster that you make with a whole רביעית revi'it of
dirty water. Okay. That's that amount of plaster.
ואילו בתר דגבליה, ve-ilu batar de-gableh,
before it's been mixed into plaster- I'm sorry, after it's been mixed
into plaster, תניא, tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, טיט, tit,
how much plaster is significant? כדי לעשות בהן פי כור kedei la-asot
bahen pi kura
to make for the opening of the bellows used in some type
of a smelting process. And presumably that amount of plaster comes from
a mixture that, you know, from the amount of plaster you make
with a רביעית revi'it of water is much more plaster than needed
for this tiny little function. So again you have this thing. Before
it's been processed, it is a much larger size than the amount
that's significant after it's been processed. Now of course that you could
say is a little different because that you could actually say that
the object has changed, you know, but water- I mean not just
changed, but it's other other materials have been added. You know, the
other cases maybe there was some transformation but it's not like the
addition of other materials. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that. It
says the same answer it's been saying. התם נמי כדאמרין, hatam nami
kide-amrin, like we said, לפי שאין אדם טורח לגבל את הטיט לעשות
בו פי כור, lefi she-ein adam tore-ach le-gabel et ha-tit la-asot bo
pi kura, you do not bother mixing cement, mixing plaster, to get
the little amount needed for making this opening for the bellows. So
therefore, same idea. The opening for the bellows has significance. That little
amount of water, even water to be used for that, would have
significance if you would bother. But since you're not going to bother
with it, it doesn't have significance. Okay. So it's not a question
about it being early, it's a question about whether you're going to
actually bother to use that little amount. תא שמע, ta shema, come
and hear, we're going to try again. דאמר רבי חייא בר אמי
משמיה דעולא, de-amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ami mishmeh de-Ulla, רבי חייא בר
אמי Rabbi Chiya bar Ami said in the name of עולא, Ulla,
by the way, I should also- well, you know, fine.
שלושה עורות הן, sheloshah orot hen, there are three types of leathers.
מצה חופה ודיפתרא. matza chipa ve-diftera. Okay. Those are just their names.
So מצה, matza, so what does מצה matza mean? כמשמעו, ke-mashmao, like
מצה, matza, means that it's completely- it's completely has like no nothing
done to it. מצה matza is just flour and water. דלא מליח,
de-lo mliach, no salt, ודלא קמיח, ve-de-lo kmiach, no flour, actually you
have flour in מצה, matza, ודלא עפיץ, ve-de-lo afitz, and is not
rubbed with gallnuts. So the basic point is nothing nothing done to
it, just flour and water. You know, we might also want to
say like thin and brittle, but okay, the מצה matza in the
גמרא Gemara was probably much more like pita than our מצהs matza
which are more like crackers, but okay. So the point is not
what it looks like, the point is is that it has no
processing done to it, just simply bread and water. So here too
it's the straight leather, the straight skin of the animal, they did
not do any of the three processes they normally did to get
it into- to process it into leather leather, which was first of
all salting it, then adding flour on top of it or somehow,
and then rubbing it with
gallnuts. וכמה שיעורו, ve-kamma shi'uro, how much of this מצה matza leather
it is significant to be חייב chayav for taking it out? תני
רבי ישמאל בר רבי יהודה, tani Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yehuda, כדי
לצור בו משקולת קטנה, kedei lutzor bo mishkalot ktana, in order to
use it to wrap small weights. Like they would have
a balance scale and you'd have fixed weights you'd put on one
side and then, you know, the fruit or the grain or whatever
you're weighing on the other side, and you want to wrap those
weights individually so they don't rub against one another and actually become
less than they're supposed to represent. So you would rub them with
this type of unworked, untamped leather. Okay, and that's the smallest use.
וכמה שיעורו, Vekamah shiuro, how much is that? כדי ליתן Kedei litten
or כדי לעשות kedei la'asot קמיע. kameia. I'm sorry, did I skip
a line? I skipped a line. וכמה שיעורו, Vekamah shiuro, how much
is that? Yeah, yeah, yeah.
שלשה—whatever. Shalsha I'm sorry. כדי—וכמה אמר Amar, אביי, Abaye, thank you, said
אביי, Abaye ריבעא דריבעא דפומבדיתא. riva deriva dePumbedisa. So it is a
quarter of a quarter of the like that's used in פומבדיתא. Pumbedisa.
רש"י Rashi says it means a quarter of a liter. So anyway,
so some type of yeah.
So one minute.
Right, I think so.
Right, right, right. Presumably that's the smallest weight. Right, so the smallest
weight is like a gram, a weight of a ריבעא, riva, a
quarter of a quarter of this liter in פומבדיתא, Pumbedisa, and the
amount of this מצה matzah leather to wrap that weight. So anyway,
so why is this relevant?
I'm sorry, I didn't finish. חיפה, Chippa, what is חיפה? chippa? דמליח
ולא קמיח. Demaliach velo kamiach. You've done the salting but you haven't
done the flouring ולא אפיץ velo apitz and you haven't rubbed the
gallnut. וכמה שיעורו, Vekamah shiuro, how much is that? כדי ליתן Kedei
litten or כדי לעשות kedei la'asot קמיע. kameia. That is when we—that's
the leather we refer to when we say the leather to make
this pouch for the amulet. That's this middle-processed leather. דיפתרא, Diftra, that
is the final
stage—or not the final but the closest to the final. It is
דמליח וקמיח, demaliach vekamiach, salted and floured ולא אפיץ, velo apitz, the
one thing not done to it is that it has not had
the gallnut rubbed on it. וכמה שיעורו, Vekamah shiuro, how much is
that? כדי לכתוב עליו את הגט. Kedei lichtov alav es haget. That
already is used as a type of essentially a קלף, klaf, you
know, some type of a parchment and can be written on. So
there, that is the amount that you use to write a גט,
get, which is actually interestingly רש"י Rashi tries—sounds like he's trying to
say that that's smaller than the amount used to—that each one of
these because it's more processed, it's a smaller amount has significance. So
right, one minute. Hold on. Right. So that somehow, you know, the
wrapping,
the קמיע kameia size is smaller than the wrapping and the גט
get is smaller than all of them. תוספות Tosafot says that doesn't—that's
totally not true. And he actually has רש"י Rashi himself admitted earlier
that something could be more valuable but have a larger size, but
because it's more valuable you don't use it for as trivial of
purposes. So it's a little ironic, but yes, once you get it
to the stage that it's actually worth able to be written on,
you're not going to use it to wrap your little, you know,
for a pouch, you're not going to use it to wrap your
weights with. So then you're going to use it to—so the most
smallest document that you would use this for is a גט, get,
and that actually is a larger amount of this more valuable object.
Okay.
And once it's finished it's called קלף, klaf, right?
Yeah, I mean, we'll actually see in a minute different types of
קלף. klaf. So anyway, okay. תניא מיהא, Tanya miha, we learned nonetheless,
כדי לעשות בו משקלות
קטנה, kedei la'asot bo mishkalot ktana, in order to wrap a small
weight.
וכמה אמר אביי, Vekamah amar Abaye, and אביי said how much is
that small weight? ריבעא דריבעא דפומבדיתא. Riva deriva dePumbedisa. So therefore,
and that is leather that has not been tanned and you—and that
goes back to my original question. Until now we've been making arguments
by analogy, but here we're going back to my original question. My
original question was unworked leather, which presumably means מצה, matzah, hasn't been
worked at all. How much? And you said the same amount as
tanned leather, which is to make a קמיע kameia pouch. But here
we say it's a different amount. We say if it's completely untanned
it's the amount to wrap around weights, not for a קמיע kameia
pouch. So look, you know, you're wrong. It's a different size. אמר,
so he said, התם בבישולא. hasam bevishula.
There it is literally cooked. רש"י Rashi says it means like moist.
There the leather is completely like somehow
fresh where it's for wrapping the weights. It hasn't begun to dry
out at all and that puts it in a completely different category.
So presumably—I mean I have no idea how you do this, but
presumably you skin the animal, you let it—you lay it in the
sun. Every time thinking about whenever I go to like מצדה, Masada,
you know, they walk you around and they show you where they
did the leather tanning, you know, when you go to these various
sites in ישראל. Yisrael. But anyway, presumably there'd be a period where,
you know, you wouldn't even start yet this processing. It would be
very moist and you'd have to dry it out. So that type
of a case, that's already like a completely different category. That's not
like early in the process. That's like before the process. After it's
dried out and you're ready to begin the processing of it, then
I say it's the same as later in the process for a
קמיע, kameia, but this stage where the process, you know, it's before
even the beginning of the process, that's a different שיעור. shiur. One
minute. והתנן, Vehatnan, but one minute, we taught in the משנה, mishna,
הבגד שלשה
על שלשה, habeged shalsha al shalsha, we've seen this before. What is
the minimum size of a type of a like mat that is
significant, something to sit on, significant for טומאת מדרס? tumas medras? If
a זב zav or זבה zava sits on it, it becomes an
אב הטומאה. av hatuma. So it's שלשה על שלשה טפחים shalsha al
shalsha tefachim for a
cloth, למדרס, lemedras, for מדרס, medras, which is this טומאה tuma of
sitting on it of a זב zav and a זבה. zava. השק,
Hasak, if it's sackcloth, which is like goat's hair, ארבעה על ארבעה,
arba'a al arba'a, four by four טפחים. tefachim. העור, Ha'or, leather, ה
על ה, Hey al Hey, five by five. five by five טפחים
*Tefachim*. מפץ *Mapatz*, if it's a mat, ו על ו *Vov al
vov*, six by six. בין למדרס *Bein l'Midras*, whether it's for מדרס
*Midras*, בין למת *Bein l'Meis*, whether it's for מת *Meis*, that's crossed
out, but that goes in all of them, but we won't worry
about that right now. Anyway, והתניא ve'hatanya, עלה *v'hatanya ala*, we taught
on this: הבגד והשק והעור כשיעור לטומאה כך שיעור shiur להוצאה *Habeged
v'hasak v'haor k'shier l'tumah kach shier l'hotzaah*. That by the cloth and
the sackcloth and the leather, the same שיעור *shier* of טומאה *tumah*,
three by three, four by four, five by five, it's the same
for carrying on שבת *Shabbat*. So now we have that leather is
five by five טפחים *Tefachim*. That's a lot bigger than the amount
for wrapping a קמיע *kameia*, presumably mean untanned leather, so it's a
huge gap. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says, ההוא בקורטובלא *hahu b'kurtovla*,
that's with a קורטובלא *kurtovla*. So רש"י *Rashi* says, if you look
at רש"י *Rashi*, that's רש"י *Rashi*: מבשלו ברותחין ומתקשה לישב עליו *mevashlo
b'roschin u'miskashe l'yeishev alav*. There you actually have processed it, but a
very different type of a processing, not to make it a nice
sort of like soft and supple leather, there you've like boiled it
and made it like a hard, firm type of a leather in
order to use as a seat. So therefore, you're not going to
see that as pre-processing of the קמיע *kameia*, you actually have turned
it into... this is the end, you've actually processed it in a
way that it's going to be used as a seat and therefore
it goes by that שיעור *shier*. But if it is... so here's
the point, if it is not even yet in a state where
it's considered ready to be processed, then it has its own שיעור
*shier*, and that's the מצה *matza*, and that's the שיעור *shier* that's
used for wrapping the whatever you call it, the weights. If it
is already processed and but in a different way and it's also
never going to make it into this processing, it's been boiled and
turned into a type of a firm leather for sitting on, then
that also goes by its own שיעור *shier*. But if it's ready
to be processed and not yet processed and it's a size that
it's significant that you're going to bother to process it, because if
you're not going to process it on this size, then forget it
also, but if it's ready to be, hasn't yet been, and a
size that you're going to make the effort to process it, then
it goes by the same size it will be when the processing
is done. Michael.
I was going to say, it seems according to תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*
that the שיעור *shier* might get somewhat larger, you know, that we
had the תלתא על תלתא *tlata al tlata*, but once it's processed,
then it becomes smaller, right?
Because at the end of
the day, שתי אותיות *shtei osiyos* or just or שמע Shema. *Shema*
when it's קלף klaf *klaf*, right? שמע Shema *Shema* presumably I would
think, right? Right, right.
Right, yeah, I mean, both not one direction, it all depends on
how the thing would standardly be used. Okay, so let's take a
look at as we go on.
Right, right, no, I'm sorry, I made what?
I'm sorry, just correct, נייר *neyar* was שתי אותיות *shtei osiyos*. Right,
קלף klaf *klaf*, you were correct, קלף klaf. *klaf* is פרשה parasha,
קטנה *parsha ketana* that we're about to see.
So shouldn't it be written on processed leather?
No, it's just how it was standard use. Okay, so now let's
take a look, let's take a look now as we turn the
page. So now we're... today we're going to just finish all the
various aspects relating to קלף klaf, *klaf*. So we were dealing with
leather, but Michael was right, you know, to sort of then refer
to the idea and Charlie as well, that that's leather being used
as leather. We've also referred to things that were written, so actually
we had this one case right now where we said this, what
do you call it, the דפתרא *diftera* that you'd use it for
certain purposes for writing a גט *get*. Now we're going to see
different leathers, different not leathers, different parchments, where the משנה mishna, *Mishnah*
said קלף klaf *klaf* is enough to write פרשה parsha קטנה שבתפילין
*parsha ketana she-bitfillin*, to write the פרשה *parsha* שמע Shema ישראל *Shema
Yisrael*.
And והיה אם שמוע ve-haya im shamo'a *v'haya im shamoa*, right?
No, just שמע Shema ישראל *Shema Yisrael*, because that fits in one
of the boxes of the of the תפילין tefillin, *Tefillin*, okay, so
of the תפילין tefillin של ראש shel rosh *Tefillin shel rosh*. So
even that amount of parchment is significant, has a ritual function, has
a function. ורמינהו *U'reminhu*: so קלף klaf כדי Kedei לכתוב עליו פרשה
קטנה *klaf k'dei lichtov alav parsha ketana*, so let's take a look.
ורמינהו *U'reminhu*, I'll ask you on this: קלף klaf. ודוכסוסטוס כדי לכתוב
עליו מזוזה mezuza. *Klaf v'duchsustus k'dei lichtov alav mezuzah*. So a קלף
klaf *klaf* and דוכסוסטוס duchsustus *duchsustus* is the size to write a
מזוזה mezuza *mezuzah*. So a מזוזה mezuza. *mezuzah* is שמע והיה אם
שמוע ve-haya im shamo'a. *Shema v'haya im shamoa*. So we'll worry about
דוכסוסטוס duchsustus *duchsustus* and what that is in a minute, but for
now let's focus on קלף klaf *klaf*. קלף klaf, *Klaf* to writing
a מזוזה mezuza, *mezuzah* is שמע והיה אם שמוע *Shema v'haya im
shamoa*, not just שמע *Shema*. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says: מאי
מזוזה mezuza *mai mezuzah*? What does מזוזה mezuza. *mezuzah* mean? מזוזה mezuza
שבתפילין *Mezuzah she-bitfillin*. It means one of the parchments in the תפילין
tefillin *Tefillin*. Okay, it doesn't mean מזוזה mezuza. *mezuzah*, which is funny
because מזוזה mezuza. *mezuzah* means a doorframe, it doesn't mean a parchment,
but somehow apparently, which is not a חידוש *chiddush*, that these words
started changing their meaning, so מזוזה mezuza *mezuzah* could mean like a
scrolled up little a little scrolled up scroll. Okay, so therefore it's
one of the scrolls in the
תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*. והתניא v'ha tanya, *V'hatanya*, וקרי
להו לתפילין מזוזה mezuza *v'kari lehu l'Tefillin mezuzah*? Would you call a
scroll in the תפילין tefillin? *Tefillin* a מזוזה mezuza *mezuzah*? Yes. והתניא
*V'hatanya*, I'll show you, we taught in a ברייתא braita, *braita*. והתניא
*V'hatanya* sometimes a proof, not a challenge. והתניא *V'hatanya*, we taught in
a ברייתא baraisa: *braita*: רצועות שבתפילין עם התפילין מטמאות את הידיים בפני
עצמן *Retzuos she-bitfillin im ha-Tefillin metamos es ha-yadayim bifnei atzman*. The straps
of תפילין tefillin, *Tefillin* with the תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*, if you remember,
right, כתבי הקודש *kisvei ha-kodesh* are מטמאים את הידיים *metamei es ha-yadayim*,
going back to the first פרק *perek*, one of the things בית
הלל *Beis Hillel* בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* decided upon. So
now how about the things that the straps of תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*?
So yes, when they are connected to the תפילין tefillin, *Tefillin*, they
have the same status as the תפילין tefillin, *Tefillin* itself and they're
also
מטמאות
את הידיים *metamos es ha-yadayim*. בפני עצמן *Bifnei atzman*, if they're by
themselves. עד שיגע בקציצה *ad sheyigah baktzitzah* that if you touch the
רצועה *ratzua* even when it's attached to the תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*, you're
טהור *tahor*. It does not have the status of extended כתבי קודש
*Kitvei Kodesh* unless you actually touch the box itself, not the box
like we store them in, the actual cube in which the פרשיות
parshiyos, *parshiyot* are, in which the פרשיות *parshiyot* are. Okay, only that
is considered connected to the תפילין tefillin. *Tefillin*, the פרשיות *parshiyot* directly
to cause טומאה *tumah*. Okay, רבי זכאי משמיה אמר *Rabbi Zakkai mishmeih
omer*, רבי זכאי *Rabbi Zakkai* said in his name, טהור עד שיגע
במזוזה עצמה *tahor ad sheyigah bimzuzah atzmah*. No, forget it, no part
of the תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* causes טומאה *tumah* of כתבי קודש *Kitvei
Kodesh* until you actually touch the scroll itself. For us, exactly. So
for us what's important is he calls the parchment itself in the
תפילין tefillin. *Tefillin* a מזוזה mezuza *mezuzah*. Okay, so that's how we've
reconciled it. It's not to write a מזוזה mezuza *mezuzah*, it's to
write a פרשה *parshah* of תפילין tefillin. *Tefillin* שלמה *shleimah*. הגמרא *haGemara*
says one minute, הא דמתניא סיפא *ha dematnya seifa*, the end of
that ברייתא braisa. *braita* that says קלף klaf, ודוכסוסטוס *klaf v'duchsustus* is
to write מזוזה mezuza. *mezuzah*, says קלף klaf, כדי לכתוב עליו פרשה
קטנה שבתפילין ששמע ישראל *klaf k'dei lichtov alav parshah ktanah shebitfillin she'Shema
Yisrael*. It's a very contradictory ברייתא *braita*. It says קלף klaf ודוכסוסטוס
*klaf v'duchsustus* to write a מזוזה mezuzah *mezuzah*, קלף klaf *klaf* to
write the small פרשה *parshah* in the תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* of שמע
ישראל *Shema Yisrael*. So מכלל דרישא *michlal d'reisha* when it so he
wants to say a small פרשה *parshah* of תפילין tefillin *Tefillin*, it
says it. So when it said in the beginning מזוזה mezuzah, *mezuzah*,
במזוזה עצמה עסקינן *bimzuzah atzmah askinan*, we're talking about a real מזוזה
mezuzah, *mezuzah*. Fine, but it's not a question on our משנה Mishnah,
*mishnah*, it's a ברייתא *braita* that doesn't make sense. It starts by
saying קלף klaf. ודוכסוסטוס *klaf v'duchsustus* to write a מזוזה mezuzah. *mezuzah*
and then it says קלף klaf *klaf* in order to write שמע
ישראל *Shema Yisrael*. So which one is it? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says מכלל דרישא מזוזה mezuzah, עצמה עסקינן *michlal d'reisha mezuzah atzmah
askinan*. הכי קתני *hachi katani*. No, no, no, this is how you
have to read this ברייתא *braita* because anyway it's contradictory. קלף klaf,
ודוכסוסטוס שיעורן בכמה *klaf v'duchsustus shiuran b'kamah*, meaning
קלף klaf, ודוכסוסטוס *klaf v'duchsustus* how much? דוכסוסטוס duchsustus. כדי לכתוב עליו
מזוזה mezuzah? *duchsustus k'dei lichtov alav mezuzah*. If it's דוכסוסטוס duchsustus *duchsustus*,
then it's the size of a מזוזה mezuzah *mezuzah* and now we
really do mean a full מזוזה mezuzah? *mezuzah*, שמע והיה אם שמוע
*Shema v'Hayah Im Shamoa*. קלף klaf כדי לכתוב עליו פרשה קטנה שבתפילין
ששמע ישראל *klaf k'dei lichtov alav parshah ktanah shebitfillin she'Shema Yisrael*. But
קלף klaf, *klaf* goes by the שמע ישראל *Shema Yisrael* פרשה *parshah*.
It is when it says קלף klaf. ודוכסוסטוס כדי לכתוב עליו *klaf
v'duchsustus k'dei lichtov alav*, it probably read and this makes a lot
of sense that this is a textual type of a mistake that
you make by skipping words which I seem to be doing a
lot today. It would have read קלף klaf, ודוכסוסטוס דוכסוסטוס duchsustus. כדי
לכתוב עליו פרשה שבמזוזה קלף klaf. כדי לכתוב פרשה שבי *klaf v'duchsustus
duchsustus k'dei lichtov alav parshah shebimzuzah klaf k'dei lichtov parshah shebi*... so
the first word the second דוכסוסטוס duchsustus *duchsustus* fell out, right? Can
you all understand it because it's two times the same word? קלף
klaf. ודוכסוסטוס דוכסוסטוס duchsustus כדי *klaf v'duchsustus duchsustus k'dei*. So you know
you could say that that's a mistake that it says דוכסוסטוס duchsustus
*duchsustus* twice. But anyway, so it's a very nice textual reconstruction. And
now we know that דוכסוסטוס duchsustus, *duchsustus* would be for the whole
מזוזה mezuzah, *mezuzah*, קלף klaf *klaf* for שמע ישראל *Shema Yisrael*. So
what does that tell you? It tells you that they would use
different leather, different קלפים *klafim* for תפילין tefillin, *Tefillin* and for מזוזה
mezuzah, *mezuzah*. For מזוזה mezuzah? *mezuzah* they would use a parchment called
the דוכסוסטוס duchsustus. *duchsustus* and for and for תפילין tefillin. *Tefillin* they'd
use a parchment called קלף klaf, *klaf*. And therefore if you have
the מזוזה Mezuzah *mezuzah* type of parchment, it's the size to write
a מזוזה mezuzah. *mezuzah* because you can't write a מזוזה mezuzah. *mezuzah*
on two separate pieces of parchment. You'd have to write it on
one piece, both פרשיות *parshiyot*. If it's the קלף klaf, *klaf* type,
the תפילין tefillin *Tefillin* type of parchment, then it's enough to write
one פרשה *parshah* of שמע *Shema* because that is put in its
own box. Now what is the difference between דוכסוסטוס duchsustus. *duchsustus* and
קלף klaf. *klaf*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will be discussing this
but I will just show you very simply here's what it is
and in these days we usually use the same thing but I'll
talk about that in a minute. Okay, so here is your
animal, here's your cow says
moo, okay, moo, anyway, but this is the leather on the animal.
Obviously here is the real sort of skin underneath but we've blown
up the leather for these purposes. So the way you remember this
is קלף klaf? *klaf*, קלוף *kaluf* means to peel. So you peel
things that are the outer layer. Okay, so what they would do
is they would separate these two. They would take the whole sort
of skin and cut it into and in half. The bottom half
would be called דוכסוסטוס duchsustus *duchsustus* whatever and the top half would
be called like the peel, קלף klaf, *klaf*. Okay, and they would
use these for different writing. They would both of them they would
write in the area that they would connect. Okay, that apparently would
be so where it's peeled away from presumably creates an easier area
for writing. So the קלף klaf. *klaf* would be written on the
underside, the דוכסוסטוס duchsustus, *duchsustus* you know after you separated it it
was the place where
they which which is the part nearer to the hair?
Near the hair. That's why I drew the face over here. Here
are the legs, here's the hair, okay, this is the skin, this
is not the skin, the flesh. Okay. Okay, so anyway you peeled
it apart, the skin apart and the area where they're connecting is
what you would write on the bottom of the קלף klaf. *klaf*
as it were and the top of the דוכסוסטוס duchsustus *duchsustus*. And
as we'll see in a minute this whole thing taken as one
unit is called גויל gevil *gevil*. Okay, so the קלף klaf *klaf*
would be written for מזוזה mezuzah? *mezuzah*, דוכסוסטוס duchsustus? *duchsustus* for I
mean this is for תפילין tefillin, *Tefillin*. And this is for מזוזה.
Mezuzah
And why is there a difference? You know, a lot of this
is just assumed to be הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha lemoshe misinai, some
also speculate that maybe the this thing made out of קלף klaf?
is easier to twist, and you have to twist it at a
very small, fold it into small things to fit in the תפילין,
tefillin but these are seen as not just convenience things but actual
very absolute הלכות, halachot, this difference. Okay? So let's take a look
now
what we'll do today later.
Yeah. So let's take a look. So אמר רב, Amar Rav, so
now we have established that the קלף klaf, goes by the amount
needed for תפילין tefillin and the דוכסוסטוס duchsustus amount needed for מזוזה.
mezuzah So now we're going to look at that real question, are
they really divided in such absolute terms that way? אמר רב, Amar
Rav, said רב, Rav, דוכסוסטוס הרי היא כקלף. duchsustus harei hi keklaf.
You know what? דוכסוסטוס duchsustus has the same הלכה halacha of קלף.
klaf. מה קלף כותבין עליו תפילין, ma klaf kotvin alav tefillin, the
same we write תפילין tefillin on קלף, klaf. אף דוכסוסטוס כותבין עליו
תפילין, af duchsustus kotvin alav tefillin, you write תפילין tefillin. on דוכסוסטוס.
duchsustus So okay, then why wouldn't it be by the same שיעור
of תפילין? tefillin. Right, if you use דוכסוסטוס duchsustus for תפילין, tefillin
it should be the one פרשה, שמע. So let's take a look.
תנן, tenan, we taught in a משנה, Mishnah קלף כדי לכתוב פרשה
קטנה שבתפילין שהיא שמע ישראל. klaf kedei lichtov parasha ktana shebitefillin shehi
Shema Yisrael.
קלף klaf, in, only קלף klaf, by that amount, דוכסוסטוס לאו, duchsustus
lav, not דוכסוסטוס. duchsustus So למצוה, lemitzvah,
that's because ideally you're supposed to use קלף. klaf So meaning you
really could have asked like the better question, right? Because we said
before דוכסוסטוס duchsustus goes
by the מזוזה mezuzah side, not the קלף klaf side. And the
basic answer is, yes, yes, לכתחילה lechatchila you use קלף klaf for
תפילין tefillin and דוכסוסטוס duchsustus. for מזוזה. mezuzah But בדיעבד bedieved you
can use דוכסוסטוס duchsustus for תפילין tefillin as well. So if I
have דוכסוסטוס, duchsustus I define it by the standard use. The standard
use is מזוזה, mezuzah? which is a bigger size. But בדיעבד, bedieved,
if I used it for תפילין, tefillin. it would be, I would
be יוצא yotze with דוכסוסטוס. duchsustus
So now let's see. תא שמע. ta shema.
So if you used it for תפילין, tefillin it would be חייב
chayav of that size.
If you acted then you would be like מצניע. matznia. Yeah. תא
שמע, ta shema, come in here. הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha lemoshe misinai,
and here you see it's הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha lemoshe misinai, תפילין
על הקלף ומזוזה על דוכסוסטוס. tefillin al haklaf u'mezuza al duchsustus. תפילין
tefillin is on the קלף, klaf מזוזה mezuzah on דוכסוסטוס. duchsustus. קלף
במקום בשר ודוכסוסטוס במקום שיער. klaf bimkom basar ve'duchsustus bimkom sear. It's
a funny way of describing it, but this is what I was
telling you, which is that you write it on the places that
they were connected. That's where the writing is done. So at the
קלף, klaf. the writing takes place
במקום בשר, bimkom basar, and the דוכסוסטוס duchsostus, takes place במקום שיער.
bimkom sear. You see what I mean? Relative. For the דוכסוסטוס, duchsostus.
this is the closest to the flesh, this is the closest to
the hair. For the קלף, klaf. this is the closest to the
flesh, that's the closest to the hair. So the קלף klaf you
write במקום בשר, bimkom basar, the דוכסוסטוס duchsostus. you write במקום שיער,
bimkom sear, but you're really doing the writing on them in the
place where they were both connected. Okay? So that's that.
Did you say we had דוכסוסטוס?
duchsostus, Yes, קלף במקום בשר, klaf bimkom basar, you can find one
and bring it into class. קלף במקום בשר ודוכסוסטוס במקום שיער. klaf
bimkom basar ve'duchsustus bimkom sear. So anyway you see that they're separate
categories, דוכסוסטוס duchsostus, only for מזוזה. mezuzah ולמצוה, u'lemitzvah, that's the מצוה
mitzvah the way you do it, but בדיעבד bedieved דוכסוסטוס duchsostus, you
can use for תפילין. tefillin. והתניא, but we taught in a ברייתא,
שינה פסול, shina pasul, if you changed which is which, it's invalid.
אמזוזה, a'mezuza, it means if you use קלף klaf. for מזוזה mezuzah
it's invalid, but if you used דוכסוסטוס duchsostos. for תפילין tefillin you're
still okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא... veha... You said the
opposite? All right. והא, veha,
let's take a look. והתניא שינה בזה ובזה פסול. ve'hatanya shina be'zeh
u'vezeh pasul. But one minute, it says if you switch either way,
it's no good. You have to use each leather for its own
purpose, each parchment for its own purpose. So אידי ואידי מזוזה. aidi
ve'aidi mezuza. No, it means that you change with a מזוזה. mezuzah.
But there are two ways you could do something wrong with a
מזוזה. mezuzah הא דכתביה אקלף במקום שיער, ha de'katvei a'klaf bimkom sear,
one is you wrote on קלף. klaf אינמי אדוכסוסטוס במקום בשר, inamei
a'duchsustus bimkom basar, or you switched it to the writing in the
דוכסוסטוס duchsostos. to the wrong place.
So what he's saying there is דוכסוסטוס duchsostos, you can use for
תפילין.
tefillin Okay, this he's saying could be used for תפילין. tefillin, That's
what רב Rav is claiming. Okay. Doesn't it say that if you
switch either way maybe that's confusing? Okay, תפילין tefillin according to רב
Rav can be קלף klaf and דוכסוסטוס duchsostos. if necessary. Okay. מזוזה
mezuzah can only be דוכסוסטוס. duchsostos, Okay. That's saying that you can't
change. תפילין tefillin you can change, דוכסוסטוס duchsostos you can't change. So
why it says if you change either way it's no good? So
either way means if you took a מזוזה mezuzah and you did
one of two things wrong. One thing wrong you could do by
a מזוזה mezuzah. would be use קלף, klaf no good. The other
thing you could do wrong by a מזוזה mezuzah is use the
דוכסוסטוס duchsostos on the wrong side. Okay? So if you made any
change with the מזוזה mezuzah, it's no good. But if you made
your change with your תפילין, Tefillin רב Rav is claiming it's still
good. Okay. I don't get it either, it's all הלכה למשה מסיני.
halacha lemoshe misinai. Anyway, that is רב's Rav claim. You can use
דוכסוסטוס duchsostos for תפילין. Tefillin All the things that say you can't
are talking about you can't switch with מזוזה. mezuzah, But תפילין Tefillin
you can use even דוכסוסטוס. duchsostos. And he still holds on. So
the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
ואי בעית אימא, ve'i bayit eima, and if you want because I've,
you know, these have been really like weak answers, so here's a
better answer. שינה בזה ובזה תנאי היא. shina be'zeh u'vezeh tannai hi.
Fine, it's a debate of תנאים. tannaim. So there are those that...
say you can't switch for תפילין, Tefillin but רב Rav doesn't agree
with it. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in the ברייתא: שינה בזה ובזה
פסול. shina b'zeh u'v'zeh pasul. If you switch either way, you use
for the מזוזה mezuzah. you use קלף, klaf for the תפילין Tefillin
דוכסוסטוס, duchsostos no good. רבי אחא מכשיר משום רבי אחא ברבי חנינא
ואמרי לה משום רבי יעקב ברבי חנינא. Rabbi Acha machshir mishum Rabbi
Acha barbi Chanina v'amri lah mishum Rabbi Yaakov barbi Chanina. רבי אחא
Rabbi Acha says it's okay in the name of either of these
two תנאים. Tannaim. So it sounds like by the way he says
it's okay to switch both directions. רב Rav didn't say that, but
minimally it can be read to say like רב, Rav, for תפילין
Tefillin if בדיעבד bedi'eved you can use דוכסוסטוס. duchsostos, So that's רב's
Rav claim, although most of the evidence seems to say they remain
absolutely separate. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues, we're not done yet.
אמר רב... Amar Rav... wait
a minute...
I'm sorry, I put the period in the wrong place. Okay, I'm
sorry, I put the period in the wrong place because those were
אמר רב Amar Rav not סימני... simanei... I'm sorry. So it should
have been רבי אחא מכשיר, Rabbi Acha machshir, period. רבי אבא Rabbi
Abba says it's good. Now the גמרא Gemara
says... משום... mishum... am I reading this right? משום רבי אחי ברבי
חנינא ואמרי לה משום רבי יהושע ברבי חנינא... mishum Rabbi Achi barbi
Chanina v'amri lah mishum Rabbi Yehoshua barbi Chanina... no, okay, I did
it right the first time. Last time I thought I was mistaken,
I was wrong. רבי אחא מכשיר. Rabbi Acha machshir. So רבי אחא
Rabbi Acha in the name of either רבי אחי Rabbi Achi or
רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov is also...
he says that it is okay to switch, and for רב Rav
it would mean at least okay to switch from קלף klaf, to
תפילין Tefillin to even use דוכסוסטוס. duchsostos Now the גמרא Gemara continues.
רב פפא אמר, רב דאמר כתנא דבי מנשה. Rav Pappa amar, Rav
de-amar ke-tanna de-vei Menashe. רב פפא Rav Pappa has a different answer.
Not that he says like this רבי אחא Rabbi Acha who says
you can't switch, but he says like תנא דבי מנשה. tanna de-vei
Menashe. דתנא דבי מנשה, De-tanna de-vei Menashe, we taught from the school
of מנשה: Menashe: כתבה על הנייר ועל המטלית פסולה. kesavah al ha-niyar
v'al ha-matlis psulah. If it was written on a... what?
What was written?
Presumably the פרשה of the תפילין. Tefillin Okay, let's take a look.
The גמרא Gemara is going to figure it out though, okay, the
גמרא Gemara is about to analyze it. If you wrote it, whatever
it is, on paper or on מטלית, matlis, which he says like
a rag, it's פסול. pasul. על הקלף ועל הגויל ועל הדוכסוסטוס כשרה.
Al ha-klaf v'al ha-gevil v'al ha-duchsostus kesherah. If you wrote it however
on any three of the possibilities, right? A קלף, the גויל gevil.
which is the whole thing, or the דוכסוסטוס, duchsostos, any three of
those is okay,
כשרה. kesherah. So כתבה מאי? kesavah mai? What are you writing on
these parchments? אילימא מזוזה? I-leima mezuzah? If you're talking about מזוזה, mezuzah.
מזוזה אקלף מי כתבינן? mezuzah a-klaf mi kasvinan? We've been very consistent
saying that you cannot switch מזוזה, only דוכסוסטוס, duchsostos you cannot write
it on קלף. So we cannot be talking about מזוזה. אלא לאו
תפילין? Ela lav tefillin? Must be talking about תפילין. Tefillin. So you
see there's an opinion that תפילין Tefillin, can have a range of
legitimate parchments. It could be דוכסוסטוס, duchsostos it could be קלף, it
could even be גויל. gevil? So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
גויל? gevil? ולטעמיך
תפילין אגויל מי כתבינן? U-le-tameich tefillin a-gevil mi kasvinan? You can't say
תפילין Tefillin. because who says you can write תפילין Tefillin, on גויל?
אלא... Ela... and it doesn't even quote any evidence against it, it
just says nobody has ever suggested that. So it can't be talking
about מזוזה, can't be talking about תפילין. Tefillin. So what is that
magic thing that can be written on one of three things? What's
left after תפילין Tefillin, and מזוזה? ספר תורה!
Sefer
Torah!
אלא כי תניא ההיא בספר תורה. Ela ki tanya hahi be-Sefer Torah.
That's talking about a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, that can be written
in any of those three. But תפילין and מזוזה maybe each have
their own, and you have no proof to רב Rav that you
can
switch by תפילין. So the גמרא says: לימא מסייע ליה. Leima mesayei
lei. Let me try to bring a proof to you. כיוצא בו,
Keyotzei vo, similar to this idea that you cannot take... there's a
משנה, you know, it says you cannot
take your תפילין שביד tefillin she-be-yad and... תפילין שבראש she-ba-rosh and use
it for your של יד, shel yad, but you could take your
של יד shel yad and use it for your של ראש because
מעלין בקודש ולא מורידין. ma'alin ba-kodesh v'lo moridin. And then it goes
on and says כיוצא בו keyotzei vo in a similar
fashion: תפילין שבלו וספר תורה שבלו אין עושים מהם מזוזה. Tefillin she-balu
ve-Sefer Torah she-balu ein osin mei-hem mezuzah. If your תפילין wore away
or your ספר תורה Sefer Torah wore away, can you take out
the one parchment that you need to make a מזוזה? No! לפי
שאין מורידין מקדושה חמורה לקדושה קלה. Lefi she-ein moridin mi-kedusha chamura l'kedusha
kala. ספר תורה Sefer Torah is seen as a higher קדושה kedusha
and תפילין is a higher קדושה kedusha than מזוזה, you know, more
parchments, more פרשיות, and therefore you cannot go ahead and put them
in a מזוזה, you cannot go down in קדושה. kedusha. By the
way, how could you have ever used the... you could understand how
you could have used the ספר תורה Sefer Torah for תפילין, you
go to the right places and you cut them out. But how
do you use it for מזוזה? מזוזה has to have שמע and
והיה אם שמוע on one piece of parchment. In a ספר תורה...
Sefer Torah... no... so תוספות Tosfos says maybe... no, you had
שמע at the bottom of a column and you cut it out
with the white space below and then you wrote in the והיה
אם שמוע. So that's how you would want to use the שמע
from a ספר תורה Sefer Torah for a מזוזה. One minute, let's
see what it says. So the גמרא says:
טעמא דאין מורידין. Ta'ama de-ein moridin. The only problem is because you
can't go down, because of this rule of, you know, going up
in קדושה kedusha not going down. הא מורידין, Ha moridin, if that
wasn't a problem, if you could go down, עושין. osin. In theory,
you could use ספר תורה Sefer Torah and תפילין for a מזוזה.
So what is this magic thing that the ספר תורה Sefer Torah
is written on that in theory and the תפילין are written on
that in theory they could be used for a מזוזה? Okay, so
דכתב מאי? de-kasav mai? What is it written on? לאו דכתב א...
Lav de-kasav a... Obviously תפילין can be written on something that can
be used for a מזוזה in theory, not for this rule about
not מורידין. moridin. So you say that תפילין can be written on
דוכסוסטוס. That's a very nice proof. גמרא says לא דכתיבא אקלף. lo
d'chtiva a'klaf. No, the מזוזה was written on a קלף. For all
along we've been saying, right, מזוזה absolutely דוכסוסטוס. תפילין is what we're
talking. And now in the end we completely reverse it. תפילין has
to be קלף. דוכסוסטוס, I mean the מזוזה you have a choice,
could be קלף or could be דוכסוסטוס. Okay, so דכתיבא אקלף d'chtiva
a'klaf and therefore the תפילין was written on the קלף, the ספר
תורה Sefer Torah was written on the קלף, and the thinking was,
can you use it for מזוזה? So now we're doing the exact
opposite of רב. Rav. תפילין are locked in, מזוזה could even use
a קלף. ומזוזה אקלף מי כתבינן? u'mezuzah a'klaf me katvinan? Do we
really write a מזוזה on a קלף? אין, in, yes, והתניא, we've
done a ברייתא. כתבה אקלף על הנייר ועל המטלית פסולה. katva a'klaf,
al ha'nyar, v'al ha'matlis pesula. If you wrote it on קלף, or
on paper, or on rags, it's invalid. אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר,
amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar said, רבי מאיר היה כותב על הקלף. Rabbi Meir haya kosev
al ha'klaf. I've gotta tell you רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would write
on a קלף. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was actually a סופר, sofer,
and other גמרות Gemaras discuss that. He would write it on a
קלף. מפני שמשתמרת mipnei she'misameress because actually a קלף is more, you
know, durable. So he would write it, whatever this smachet it is.
So the גמרא says, it assumes that this it is got to
be מזוזה because it's something that the question is, do you write
it on a קלף? So we said that a ספר
תורה Sefer Torah obviously can be written on a קלף, תפילין obviously
could be written on a קלף. So the only thing that there's
a question about is the מזוזה. And here we're finding out that
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you can write a מזוזה on קלף.
השתא דאתית להכי, hashata d'asis l'hachi, so now what have we, now
we've said מזוזה must be דוכסוסטוס, I'm sorry,
תפילין must be קלף, מזוזה can be either. Now that we're saying
that, let's turn רב Rav into that. לרב נמי לא
תימא דוכסוסטוס הרי כקלף. l'Rav nami lo teima duchsostos harei k'klaf. When
רב Rav said, you know, equated דוכסוסטוס to קלף, we got it
wrong. He wasn't saying דוכסוסטוס was as good and you could use
דוכסוסטוס for
תפילין. אלא אימא קלף הרי כדוכסוסטוס. ella eima klaf harei k'duchsostos. He's
saying that the קלף counted as good as דוכסוסטוס. דוכסוסטוס can't be
used for other things, but קלף can be used for other
things. ומה דוכסוסטוס כותבין עליו מזוזה אף קלף כותבין עליו מזוזה. u'mah
duchsostos kotvin alav mezuzah af klaf kotvin alav mezuzah. So what we
had said was the exact opposite. It sounded like רב Rav said
not only can you use קלף for תפילין, you can use דוכסוסטוס,
they're equal, they can both be used for תפילין.
No, they cannot both be used for תפילין, only קלף for תפילין.
But they are equal in the sense that they can both be
used for מזוזה.
The same way you can write a מזוזה with דוכסוסטוס you could
write קלף. ספר תורה Sefer Torah with anything. Anyway, תוספות Tosfos, has
a whole discussion because the way they would make leather, I just
want to read the first line of תוספות, Tosfos he says,
actually one
minute, בקלפים שלנו b'klafim shelanu three lines down in the narrow
lines, יש להם דין קלף yesh lahem din klaf וכותבין עליהם ספר
תורה תפילין ומזוזה. v'kosvin aleihem Sefer Torah, Tefillin, u'mezuzah. When we end,
we decide that there's one thing you can use for everything: קלף.
Right, קלף you started with מזוזה, now we've ended and said you
could use it, we started saying תפילין, we ended saying you could
use it for מזוזה, right, and we also said you could use
it for ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. So תוספות Tosfos says, so it
must be because we use one type of parchment for all of
our stuff. So it must be the stuff we use is called
קלף. But then he's got a little bit of a problem because,
you know, because קלף is described in this very particular way and
that's not exactly how they would make their parchment. So the rest
of the תוספות tries to figure out, it's gotta be in the
קלף category because we use it for all three and that's the
only thing you can use for all three, and then he figures
out how we say that what we do puts our parchment into
the קלף category. But that explains also why the משנה said that
קלף is to write the פרשיות שבתפילין parshiyos she'ba'Tefillin because that's the
smallest use you can use with קלף, and דוכסוסטוס, the only thing
you use דוכסוסטוס for is a מזוזה. So therefore the size of
דוכסוסטוס is the size to write a מזוזה.